Inventory of the Albert H. Arkus papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Albert H. Arkus papers
1952-1998
2011C21
Arkus, Albert H.
10 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 2 cassette boxes (5.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection relates mainly to technical and personnel aspects of Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty broadcast operations, in particular at the New York Programming Center. It is comprised of correspondence, memoranda, newswires, reports, manuals, printed matter, photographs, slides, blueprints, sound recordings, and memorabilia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty broadcast records, Hoover Institution Archives
Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty corporate records, Hoover Institution Archives
Sig Mickelson papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
March 3, 1929 Born, Henry Albert Arkus
1950 Graduated from Queens College with a degree in speech and physics Joined Radio Free Europe as a studio recording technician
1975-1994 Worked as production manager and, later, broadcasting operations director of the RFE/RL New York Programming Center
March 5, 2001 Died, Great Neck, New York
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection relates mainly to technical and personnel aspects of Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty broadcast operations, in particular at the New York Programming Center. It is comprised of correspondence, memoranda, newswires, reports, manuals, printed matter, photographs, slides, blueprints, sound recordings, and memorabilia.
One strength of this collection lies in the documentation in the Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty file of Pope John Paul II's visit to New York in 1979. Newswires provide the context for the event while the correspondence describe the steps and preparations the studio undertook for the Pope's arrival, including detailed agendas, maps of the arrival route, diagrams of designated press areas, and some photographs.
Most of the articles, clippings, and other printed matter in the collection relate to federal funding of RFE/RL, the technical complications of international broadcasting, and developments in sound and telecommunications technologies. The correspondence and memoranda in the Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty file echo these same topics, but with more focus on the broadcast transmissions and other technical and personnel operations at the New York Programming Center from the late 1970s until its closure in 1994.
The audiocassette tapes in the Sound recordings series are comprised of recordings of news programs, speaking events, and studio audio tests.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 6 series: Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty file, Photographs and Slides, Printed matter, Sound recordings, Computer disks, and Memorabilia
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Radio Free Europe.; Radio Liberty.; Radio broadcasting--Europe, Eastern.; Radio broadcasting--Soviet Union.
Collection Contents
- Radio Free Europe and Radio Liberty file, 1952-1998; 1-7, 13 (Box 1-7, 13)
  Consists of clippings, reports, memoranda, correspondence, newswires, photographs, and ephemera.
  Arranged in four groups: General, Administrative operations, Broadcast operations, and Blueprints then alphabetically by physical form or by subject in some cases.
  - General, 1972-1993 and undated (Folder 1-2)
    - Address books and telephone directories, 1983 and undated (Folder 1: 1-5)
    - Background information on RFE/RL and New York Programming Center, 1976 (Folder 1: 6-7)
    - Clippings and collected writings, 1972-1993 (Folder 1-2)
      - 1972-1977 (Folder 1: 8)
      - 1980-1987 (Folder 1: 9)
      - 1991-1992 (Folder 1: 10-11)
      - 1993-1994 (Folder 2: 1)
    - Name tag and press passes, 1986-1992 (Folder 2: 2)
    - RFE/RL souvenir notebook, 1980s (Folder 2: 3)
  - Administrative operations, 1955-1998 (Folder 2-5)
    - Director's Guild of America, 1965-1993 (Folder 2)
      - General, 1969 (Folder 2: 4)
      - Collective bargaining agreements, 1965-1973 (Folder 2: 5-6)
      - Memoranda and correspondence, 1955-1993 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Memoranda and correspondence, 1971-1998 (Folder 2-3)
      - Chronological, 1971-1998 and undated (Folder 2-3)
        Includes the New York Programming Center and RFE/RL corporate offices and correspondence printed out from the arkusa@rfel.org email account
        - Undated (Folder 2: 8)
        - 1971-1980 (Folder 2: 9-11)
        - 1984-1995 (Folder 9: 12-14)
        - 1997-1998 (Folder 3: 1)
      - From Glenn Ferguson to Board of Directors, 1979-1982 (Folder 3: 2)
    - Personnel, 1980-1993 (Folder 3)
      - Albert H. Arkus permanent file, 1980-1993 (Folder 3: 3)
      - News and Current Affairs Style and Procedure Manual, 1992 July (Folder 3: 4)
      - Performance reviews, 1985-1993 and undated (Folder 3: 5-11)
      - Policies and related memoranda, 1990-1993 (Folder 3: 12-14)
      - Salary schedules, 1983, 1991-1993 (Folder 3: 15)
    - Printed matter, 1984-1998 (Folder 3: 16)
      Includes an assortment of pamphlets published by RFE/RL
    - Printed matter, 1988-1993 (Folder 4: 1-2)
      Includes issues of Shortwaves, a monthly publication for RFE/RL employees
    - Reports and studies, 1968-1993 (Folder 4-5)
      - RFE technical facilities report, 1968 (Folder 4: 3)
      - Corporate affairs weekly reports, 1976-1977 (Folder 4: 4-6)
      - Research and analysis of eastern European countries, 1980 (Folder 4: 7)
      - Board of International Broadcasting annual reports and related materials, 1981-1993 (Folder 4: 8-10)
      - Computer history and modernization program, circa 1988 (Folder 4: 11)
      - Integrated network study, 1991 January (Folder 5: 1)
      - Washington D.C. studio monthly reports, 1993 September (Folder 5: 2)
    - RFE/RL Annex, 1993-1995 (Folder 5: 3-5)
      Includes schedules and memoranda relating to the shut down of the New York Programming Center
  - Broadcast operations, 1952-1998 (Folder 5-7)
    - General, 1992 (Folder 5: 6)
    - Coverage of special events, 1979-1995 (Folder 5-6)
      Includes correspondence, newswires, maps, planning materials, brochures, and photographs
      - Pope John Paul II's visit to U.S., 1979 (Folder 5: 7-15)
      - Winter Olympic Games, Lake Placid, 1980 (Folder 5: 16)
      - Winter Olympic Games, Lake Placid, 1980 (contd.) (Folder 6: 1)
      - Winter Olympic Games, Calgary, 1988 (Folder 6: 2)
      - Other sports and sporting events, 1989-1995 (Folder 6: 3)
    - Interview transcripts, 1966-1976 (Folder 6: 4)
    - Media credentials, 1995-1998 (Folder 6: 5)
    - Newsletters, 1971-1972 (Folder 6: 6)
    - Newswires, 1976-1993 (Folder 6: 7-10)
    - Press kits, 1971-1972 and undated (Folder 7: 1)
    - Program schedules, 1952-1953, 1973-1987 (Folder 7: 2-3)
    - Report, 1992 October (Folder 7: 4)
    - Telecommunications technology pamphlets, instructions, and other documentation, 1988-1993 (Folder 7: 5-7)
    - Miscellany, 1979-1993 (Folder 7: 8)
      Includes notes, diagrams of office furniture, and photocopy of sheet music
- Photographs and Slides, 1960s-1970s; 7 (Box 7:)
  Color photographs, negatives, and slides grouped by format
  - Slides depicting RFE reporters at work, broadcast towers and infrastructure, and maps, 1960s (Folder 7: 9-10)
  - RFE/RL staff, probably at New York Programming Center, 1970s (Folder 7: 11-14)
- Printed matter, 1980-1995; 11 (Box 8)
  Consists of newspapers, clippings, magazines, journals, and brochures, arranged alphabetically by format
  - Clippings and newspapers, 1980-1993 (Folder 8: 1-2)
    Includes some photocopies
  - European Broadcasting Union journals, 1988-1990 (Folder 8: 3-4)
  - Production music catalog, undated (Folder 8: 5)
  - Sound engineering magazines, 1992-1993 (Folder 8: 6-9)
  - Sound engineering societies flyers, 1992-1995 (Folder 8: 10)
- Sound recordings, 1968-1995; 8-10 (Box 9-11)
  Consists of 1/4-inch sound tape reels and audiocassette tapes, arranged by format, chronologically
  - 1/4-inch sound tape, 1968-1986 and undated (Folder 9)
    - Environmental crisis #1-RFE-Arkus-Benton, undated (Folder 9:)
    - Attn: Mr. Albert Arkus, undated (Folder 9:)
    - "This is New York," the New York Production Center, RFE/RL Inc., undated (Folder 9:)
    - 10 programs from Mexico (TDR), Czech, Hungarian, and Bulgarian, 1968 October 25 (Folder 9:)
    - Announcer training studio recording of Mary Ozga, 1972 December 21 (Folder 9:)
    - Article of the Day and Panorama #264 Tape 1, 1975 January 10 (Folder 9:)
    - For the Romanian Desk-Panorama (2 items), Tinerama (1 item)-T. Sto'an, 1975 August 19 (Folder 9:)
    - For Kratch, [unidentified], Russian, Tatar, Bulgarian, Belarusian, Latvian, Estonian, jamming, 1986 May (Folder 9:)
  - Audiocassette tapes, 1970s-1995 (Folder 10-11)
    - Undated (Folder 10)
      - Unidentified (Folder 10: 1-2)
      - Arkus, undated (Folder 10: 3)
      - Sound recording of proceedings of RFE/RL meeting in Munich, undated (Folder 10: 4-6)
      - Interview with Ernst and Lory Wallfisch, undated (Folder 10: 7)
      - Sample of production music, undated (Folder 10: 8)
      - RFE/RL test recording, undated (Folder 10: 9)
      - Sound system test, undated (Folder 10: 10)
      - Health insurance benefits for RFE/RL employees, undated (Folder 10: 11)
      - News piece on strokes and American diet, undated (Folder 10: 12)
      - Recording of phone call to San Antonio sheriff's office by RFE/RL New York Programming Center regarding Romanian man shot by secret service, undated (Folder 10: 13)
      - Hungarian programming, undated (Folder 10: 14-20)
        - "Go West Young Man" (Folder 10: 14-15)
        - Sing an Italian Song (Folder 10: 16)
        - Washington D.C. (Folder 10: 17)
        - Wonderful World of Disney (Folder 10: 18)
        - Bing Crosby Story (Folder 10: 19)
        - Christmas in New York (Folder 10: 20)
      - Russian news, undated (Folder 10: 21)
      - Discussion of Chernobyl nuclear disaster (side A) and a discussion about Marxism (side B), undated (Folder 10: 22)
      - New York Programming Center, undated (Folder 10: 23)
      - Two men speaking Ukrainian, undated (Folder 10: 24)
      - Discussion panel, undated (Folder 10: 25)
      - Slovakia and Georgia, undated (Folder 10: 26-27)
      - Excerpt of tape from BBC World Service, test of digital transmission, undated (Folder 10: 28)
      - Conversation between Albert H. Arkus (New York) and Tom or Dick Bodin (Munich), undated (Folder 10: 29)
      - Audio sampling of sound engineering problems, undated (Folder 10: 30)
    - 1970s (Folder 10)
      - Andre and Francoise Blanchard speaking at a rally, 1977 June 11 (Folder 10: 31)
      - Discussion between departments, received in Munich Production Center, 1977 October 14 (Folder 10: 32)
      - Comrex test received in Munich via AVD, 1978 April (Folder 10: 33)
      - Mix of recordings. Includes a recording made in the Hotel Dorobanti in Bucharest by Dennis Thompson for RFE/RL Romanian, 1978 February 25 (Folder 10: 34)
      - Conference call regarding ITT World Communications (Arkus and unidentified), 1978 July 25 (Folder 10: 35-36)
      - Mix of recordings. Includes recording of The Tomorrow Show (television program) featuring interview of Alexander Solzhenitsyn regarding American broadcasting into the Soviet Union. Also includes recording of Unesco meeting, 1978 November 20 (Folder 10: 37)
      - Radio Free Europe, 1970s (Folder 10: 38)
    - 1980s (Folder 10-11)
      - "Nazis in the U.S.," 60 Minutes, CBS, 1982 May 16 (Folder 10: 39)
      - Research Center for Religion and Human Rights in Closed Societies press conference with U.S. ambassador to Poland, Richard Davis, in attendance, 1982 October 28-29 (Folder 10: 40-42)
      - Interview with Wojciech Jaruzelski, 1983 July 21 (Folder 10: 43)
      - RFE/RL Romanian broadcast, 1983 September 9 (Folder 11: 1)
      - Reagan in Beijing, CNN news broadcast, 1984 (Folder 11: 2)
      - International League for Human Rights press conference regarding disappeared persons in Argentina, 1984 June 6 (Folder 11: 3)
      - Coverage of Summer Olympics, Los Angeles, 1984 August (Folder 11: 4-18)
      - Press conference with (probably) Elena Bonner regarding Andrei Sakharov and her experience leaving the Soviet Union, circa 1986 (Folder 11: 19)
      - News piece about jamming of RFE/RL radio waves and a recording of news programming on WCBS Albany, New York, 1988-1989 (Folder 11: 20)
      - Tom Bodin memorial, 1989 (Folder 11: 21)
      - RFE/RL news piece on communist revolution in Afghanistan, 1980s (Folder 11: 22)
    - 1990s (Folder 11)
      - Mix of recordings. Includes air traffic control radio and random clips of musical recordings, probably used for audio checks, 1991 (Folder 11: 23)
      - Coverage of Winter Olympics, Albertville, 1992 (Folder 11: 24-25)
      - Diane Rheme (NPR) interviews Dr. Joseph Duffey (Director of U.S. Information Agency), 1993 (Folder 11: 26)
      - Final Hungarian program at New York Programming Center, 1993 October 29 (Folder 11: 27)
      - Sakharov Institute and Soviet Emigré Orchestra discuss Andrei Sakharov and human rights violations in the Soviet Union, 1990s (side A) and recording of NPR programming, 1993-1994 (side B) (Folder 11: 28)
      - Federal funding for Voice of America and RFE/RL, circa 1995 (Folder 11: 29)
      - NPR news piece about RFE/RL, 1995 (Folder 11: 30)
      - Funding for RFE news broadcasts, 1990s (Folder 11: 31)
- Computer disks, undated; 12 (Box 12)
  Includes three 3 1/2-inch floppy disks and one 5 1/4-inch floppy disk
- Memorabilia, 1988 and undated; 12 (Box 12)
  Microphone clips, signs, and pin
  - Two microphone clips with RFE/RL logo, undated (Folder 12)
  - Sign from studio door, undated (Folder 12: 2)
  - Cardboard sign with Radio Free Europe logo, undated (Folder 12: 3)
  - RFE/RL pin from Winter Olympic games in Calgary, 1988 (Folder 12: 4)
- Blueprints and diagrams of the RFE/RL New York Programming Center building structure and broadcast signals, 1980 (Box 13: Oversize)